- 去村子怎么走? - 先一直向前,然后再升.
- Where is the village? - First you walk down, and then up again.
70年代末. 阿尔巴尼亚的一个村儿.
The end of the 70s. A village in Albania.
改编自真人真事.
Based on actual events.
你好. 学校在哪?
Good day. Where's the school?
直走一段右拐, 再直走.
Just walk down a bit to the right, and then straight up again.
谢谢.
Thanks.
你们在那里干什么? 离开那里!
What are you doing there? Get out of there!
你好.
Hi.
你是新来的生物老师? 你是从地拉那来的?
Are you the new biology teacher? Are you from Tirana?
我们一直在等你.我的名字是德因.
We've been waiting for you. My name is Djin.
我是地理老师也临时兼任 学校长椅修理工.
I'm the geography teacher and ocassionally the school bench repairman.
- 我名叫帕什克. - 这里很好,比地拉那（首都）更好.
- My name is Pashk. - It's good here, better than in Tirana.
- 这真好. - 这该死的锁.
- It's nice. - This damn lock.
比我想象的要好.
It's better than I expected.
生物课12点开始.
The biology lesson begins at 12PM.
你有了这一区域最好教室.
You've got the best class room in the district.
阿尔巴尼亚马列主义朋友们 要来看看.
Albanias marxist-leninistic friends are coming to have a look at it.
我们将其用于 全体教师会了.
We use it for the faculty meetings too.
你很走运. 这是给你的巨大荣誉.
You're lucky. It's a big honour for you.
到我办公室来.
Come by my office afterwards.
你也是,Pashk.
You too, Pashk.
“根据规定和传统 这有两个新口号.”
"According to the regulations and traditions here are two new slogans."
“亲爱的安德烈,你可以选择：”
"Dear Andr? you can choose between:"
“美帝是一个纸老虎,” -
"The American Imperialism is a Paper Tiger," -
“ - 和‘革命精神奋发向上!’.”
"- and 'Get the Revolution Spirit Up!'."
这是戴安娜,法语老师.
This is Diana, french teacher.
你好.
Hi.
你选哪个?
Have you chosen?
你对口号没任何意见?
Don't you have any comments on the slogans?
想知道我们怎么弄这些口号的吗?
Do you want to know how we make them?
我以前从来没有布置过, 但我肯定我会学.
I have never laid them before, but I'm sure I will learn.
Pashk将向你解释方法, 生产这些口号背后的技术.
Pashk will explain the method to you and the technology behind the production of slogans.
既然你是新来的,你可以选择.
Since you are new, you can choose.
- 我选择其中之一? - 是.哪个?
- I shall choose one of them? - Yes. Which one?
我不知道.他们都挺有趣.
I don't know. They're both interesting.
- 我同意,但两个是太多了. - 戴安娜也应有一个.
- I agree, but two are too much. - And Diana shall also have one.
你来决定.这不难.
Make up your mind. It's not hard.
我不喜欢犹豫的人.
I don't like people who hesitate.
一个是“美帝是一个纸老虎.”
The first one is: "The American Imperialism is a Paper Tiger."
另一个是“革命精神奋发向上.”
The other one: "Get the Revolution Spirit Up."
会是哪个?
What's it gonna be?
我选与精神有关的.
I'll take the other one, the one with the spirit.
它让我更容易为 此专心致志.
It's easier for me to concentrate on that.
我看帕什克 得到了很好的导师.
I see Pashk has been a good mentor.
所以,这会是你的第一个口号.
So, this will be your first slogan.
戴安娜,你得到：
Diana, you get:
“美帝是一个纸老虎.”
"The American Imperialism is a Paper Tiger.."
你为什么生闷气? 我不明白.
Why are you sulking? I don't understand it.
我理解 戴安娜同志的感受.
I understand how comrade Diana feels.
她宁愿有 有个更抒情的口号.
She would rather have had a more lyrical slogan.
但是,党委有 决定应该怎么做.
But the party comittee have decided that this is how it should be done.
如果我们想想, 这是做到这一点的最好办法.
And if we think, this is the best way to do it.
- 祝你好运,安德烈. - 谢谢.
- Good luck, Andr? - Thanks.
萨巴夫同志是数学老师.
Comrade Sabaf is the math teacher.
除此之外.
Among other things.
他也是村里的党委书记.
He is also the party secretary in the village.
所以他要负责我们所有的党务工作.
So he's got the responsibility for us and all work for the party.
你忘了你的协议!
You forgot your protocol!
要坚强,安德烈同志,坚强.
Be strong, comrade Andr? strong.
恭喜!你有个良好的开端.
Congratulations. You had a good start.
你什么意思? 我对口号一无所知.
What dou you mean? I know nothing about slogans.
我只是想帮助帕什克. 他有我的 .
I just wanted to help Pashk. He have me a sign.
真是个傻瓜!
What a fool!
堕落! 这只是纯粹的报复.
Corruption! It's nothing but pure revenge.
别摇铃了,来了.
Stop ringing the bell and come in now.
- 午安. - 请坐下.
- Good day. - Please sit down.
美帝是一个纸老虎
THE AMERICAN IMPERIALISM IS A PAPER TIGER
坐下,孩子们.
Sit down, children.
我很高兴,终于 见到你了.
I'm happy to finally have met you.
- 我的名字是... - 安德烈
- My name is... - Andr?
- 我们一起学习... - 生物!
- Together we'll learn... - Biology!
安德烈,我们用哪个口号?
Andr? which slogan did we get?
等一下.
Wait a minute.
也许是： “革命精神奋发向上”?
Maybe it was: "Get the Revolution Spirit Up"?
正确!
Correct!
真的很不错.只有23个.
Really good. Only 23.
- 23个什么? - 23个字母,安德烈. 真的很不错.只有23.
- 23 what? - 23 letter, Andr?
我听说你是新来的老师.
I hear you're the new teacher.
是这样.
That's that.
你有烟吗? 我烟草用完了.
Have you got a cigarette? I'm out of tobacco.
我没有火柴.
I haven't got any matches.
你有多少牲口?
How many animals have you got?
- 去年我有27个. - 现在呢?
- Last year I had 27. - And now?
费斯汀,我的儿子,知道. 他喜欢数数.
Festim, my son, knows that. He likes to count.
塞尔曼.
Selman.
我的名字是塞尔曼·托斯库.
My name is Selman Tosku.
这香烟味道非常好.
The cigarette tasted very good.
看这里.
Look here.
你好吗?
How are you?
一般般.
So so.
让我们出去到田里.
Let's go out to the field.
你喜欢?
How do you like that?
- 那是谁的口号? - 是老师米拉的.
- Whose slogan is that? - It's teacher M'ira's.
忘记的敌人最危险
THE MOST DANGEROUS ENEMY IS THE ONE THAT IS FORGOTTEN
老师!
Teacher!
我能拿那些字母I吗?
Can I have the I's?
- 我们怎么区分? - 模仿字母表.
- How are we supposed to divide the others? - After the alphabet.
给女孩们最简单的字母,把i 上的点和逗号给生病的孩子.
The easiest ones to the girls, and the dot over the i's or the commas to the sick ones.
把字母m都给好学生. 最难的是字母S.
And the m's to the good students. The hardest ones are the S's.
- 很难做出曲线. - 还是让你的计划好后做吧.
- It's hard to make the curves. - Then let's do it after your plans.
我也有一个字母.
I'll also have a letter.
不,不! 你俯瞰这块区域.
No, no! You'll overlook the placement.
如果这些字母歪了, 口号将受到损害.
If the letters are crooked, the slogan will be compromised.
这将是本村的耻辱!
And it will be a shame for the village!
我们开始?
Shall we begin?
- 干得好,老师. - 谢谢.
- Good work, teacher. - Thanks.
就这样. 谢谢大家.
That's all. Thank you everybody.
需要帮忙吗?
Can I help you?
不,没必要的. 我可以自己做到.
No, it's not necessary. I can do this on my own.
现在请走开!
Please. Go now!
对不起.
I'm sorry.
你和帕什克可以 总是扎堆.
You and Pashk could always get together.
戴安娜.
Diana.
“美帝是一个纸老虎”是什么意思?
What does "The American Imperialism is a Paper Tiger" mean?
“美帝是一个纸老虎”意思是...
"The American Imperialism is a Paper Tiger" means...
我们应该做到最好.
That we should do our best.
- 是你的哥哥死了吗,莱什? - 是的,萨巴夫同志,他死了.
- Is your brother dead, Lesh? - Yes, comrade Sabaf, he is dead.
- 愿你长寿. - 我的朋友也是.
- May you live long. - My friends too.
是你的哥哥死了,莱什?
Is your brother dead, Lesh?
- 是的,帕什克,他已经死了. - 愿你长寿.
- Yes, Pashk, he is dead. - May you live long.
我的朋友也是.
My friends too.
是你的哥哥死了,莱什?
Is your brother dead, Lesh?
- 是的,德因,他已经死了. - 愿你长寿.
- Yes, Djin, he's dead. - May you live long.
我的朋友也是.
My friends too.
是你的哥哥死了,莱什?
Is your brother dead, Lesh?
你是新来的老师?
Are you the new teacher?
- 是. - 你叫什么名字?
- Yes. - What's your name?
安德烈
Andr?
是的,安德烈,我的哥哥死了.
Yes, Andr? my brother is dead.
哀悼慰问.
Condolences.
我的朋友也是.
My friends too.
她恨我.
She hates me.
算了吧.在这里最重要的是要被 拥有权力的人们喜欢.
Forget it. The most important thing is to be liked by the ones who's got the power here.
特别是党.
Especially by the Party.
有一些事情 你必须明白.
There are some things you must understand.
你知道去年发生了什么吗?
Do you know what happened last year?
一位校长被逮个正着 -
A headmaster was caught red-handed -
- 当时他正和一个声誉不好的女老师乱搞.
- while he made love with a female teacher who had a bad reputation.
这导致口号被换.
It lead to the slogans being exchanged.
“国际无产阶级万岁,” 被更换为：
"Long Live the Proletariat's Internationalism," was exchanged with:
“警惕,警惕,时刻警惕.”
"On Guard, More on Guard, Always on Guard."
见鬼!
Damn!
科利,给我一个新水桶!
Koli, give me a new bucket!
病假不少.
The sick leave is high.
拿出你的作业本. 我想看看你的功课.
Bring out your notebooks. I want to see your homework.
塔米.
Tami.
你的单词变形作业在哪?
Where's your homework about metamorphose?
我还没做. 我累了,安德烈.
I haven't done it. I was tired, Andr?
- 你呢? - 我没做.
- And you? - I didn't do it.
有人写作业了吗?
Hasn't anyone made their homework?
我从口号地点步行回家 走了一个半小时.
It takes me one and a half hour to walk home from the slogans.
- 你呢? - 一样.
- And you? - Same thing.
如果只是一两个...
If it were only one, two or three...
但全班（都没写）!
But the whole class!
你觉得我该怎么办? 告诉校长?
What do you think I should do? Tell the headmaster?
- 不,安德烈.请不要! - 原谅我们这一次.
- No, Andr? please don't! - Forgive us just this one time.
你们用过我的好意了. 你们不是我的朋友.
You have used my kindness. You're not my friends.
我是你们的老师, 不是你们的朋友.
I'm your teacher, not your friend.
- 我会告诉校长. - 不.
- I'll tell the headmaster. - No.
我做作业了.
But I did my homework.
这些淘气鬼! 这是集体怠工!
Rascals! This is collective sabotage!
坐下.
Sit down.
真的.你在侮辱老师吗?
Really. So you're insulting the teacher?
他没有侮辱我. 他只是没有做功课.
He didn't insult me. He just didn't do his homework.
还有你,是谁这么冷静?
And you, who's so calm?
你也是.. 你的作业在哪?
You too.. Where's you homework?
你这小混蛋, 你没有做你的功课?
And you, little brat, haven't you done your homework?
谁说的?
Who said that?
站起来!站起来!
Stand up! Stand up!
淘气鬼!
Rascals!
如果这再发生,就告诉我,.
Just tell me if this happens again.
谢谢,我不这么想.
Thanks, I don't think so.
这没必要.
It won't be necessary.
不是每个人都会去首都.
Not everybody's going to the capital.
来吧. 我不走那条路.
Come on. I'm not going that way.
走开!你这头猪!
Get lost! Pig!
我们在这里不是 收集你留下的粪便.
We're not here to collect the dung you left.
下午好.
Good afternoon.
你有烟吗?
Have you got a cigarette?
继续.
Go on.
中国和阿尔巴尼亚是朋友, 钢的带绑在一起.
China and Albania are friends, tied together with a band of steel.
Kina（欧洲部分地区对华旧称）是修正主义国家.
Kina is a revisionistic country.
这就够了.闭嘴.
That's enough. Silence.
对不起,我说的不对. 中国是社会主义.
I'm sorry, I said wrong. China is socialistic.
苏联是修正主义.
It's the Soviet Union that's revisionistic.
谢谢,坐下. 很好,很不错.你得到一个B.
Thank you, sit down. It's good, very good. You get a B.
好,德因.这狗崽子托斯库 终于露出了本来面目!
Good, Djin. This boy puppy Tosku has let the mask fall at last!
- 你什么意思? - 你知道我的意思.
- What dou you mean? - You know what I mean.
我在等你通知我们.
I was waiting for you to inform us.
你是什么意思,萨巴夫同志?
What do you mean, comrade Sabaf?
天哪,今天你真幼稚.
Goodness, you're really playing naive today.
如果德因不希望 告诉我们发生了什么事, -
If Djin doesn't want to tell us what happened, -
- 我会.
- I will.
费斯汀·托斯库 -
Festim Tosku -
- 来自本区最革命的家庭!
- comes from one of the most revolutionary families in the district!
塞尔曼·托斯库和其他人喜欢他.
Selman Tosku and others like him.
昨天费斯汀在课堂上响亮地说, 中国是一个修正主义国家.
Yesterday Festim said quite loud in the lesson that China is a revisionistic country.
哦,是的. 现在我知道你在说什么了.
Oh, yes, that. Now I know what you're talking about.
你误导. 我知道到底发生了什么.
You're misinformed. I know what really happened.
费斯汀·托斯库 是我最好的学生之一.
Festim Tosku is one of my best students.
他经常说话太快,因为 他学会用心脏做作业.
He often talks too fast because he's learned his homework by heart.
替代了说苏联 是修正主义,他说的中国.
Instead of saying that the Soviet Union is revisionistic, he said China.
他瞬间改口. 他知道,他说的不对.
He corrected himself instantly. He knew that he said wrong.
我知道 他来自一个可疑的家庭.
I know that he's from a doubtful family.
但是,即使家人不参加 全国自由运动, -
But even if the family did not participate in the national freedom movement, -
- 那男孩没有故意的行为.
- the boy did not act deliberately.
你的意思是他是一个好学生, 但我有不同意见.
You mean that he's a good student, but I'm of a different opinion.
我经常给他困难的 字母,他应得的!
I often give him hard letters that he deserve!
另外,出了事你想给自己找借口.
Also you're trying to make excuses for what happened.
这对我校是一次不同寻常的 遗憾事件.
This is an extraordinary and regrettable event for our school.
我将不得不通报本地区党委.
I will have to inform the Party Comittee in the district about this.
萨巴夫同志,我再说一遍：
Comrade Sabaf, I repeat:
这仅仅是一个错误,一个失误.
It was just a mistake, an error.
这种行为不是 出于政治动机.
This act was not politically motivated.
只要问问其他学生.
Just ask the other students.
这正是我们要做的.
That's exactly what we're going to do.
但我们先来听听 费斯汀告诉我们什么.
But first we'll hear what Festim has to tell us.
孩子们比他们的家长更诚实-
The children are much more honest than their parents-
- 比其他伪君子更诚实.
- and other hypocrite adults.
很好.让我们干吧,萨巴夫同志.
Great. Let's do it, comerade Sabaf.
之后我们在教师会议上讨论.
After that we'll discuss this in a faculty meeting.
我们明天见.
I'll see you tomorrow.
戴安娜,稍等.
Diana, wait a moment.
戴安娜,我给你一个建议 -
Diana, let me give you an advice, -
- 为你自己好：
- for your own good:
别对党委书记表现出你的不信任.
Do not show your distrust openly to the party secretary.
但这太难以置信了!
But it's incredible!
一个年仅10岁的男生 说中国是修正主义, -
A small schoolboy barely 10 years old says that China is revisionistic, -
- 他涉嫌后援一场政治阴谋! 这真是令人难以置信.
- and he's suspected to stand behind a political conspiracy! It's unbelievable.
是否难以置信, 不是我们的问题.
Unbelievable or not, it's not our problem.
真相早晚会出来.
The truth will come out sooner or later.
我只关心 什么对你最适合,黛安娜.
I'm only concerned about what's best for you, Diana.
你必须明白,这些 会耗费你很多精力.
You must understand that these things can cost you very much.
你什么意思?
What do you mean?
你知道的比我好, 可以是多么危险 -
You know better than me, how risky it can be -
- 获得批准, 回家歇几天.
- to get permission to travel home for a few days.
你知道是怎么回事 -
You know how it is -
- 当你得到一个挺长的口号.
- when you get a long slogan.
你知道有一个很长的口号 是什么意思!
You know what it means to have a very long slogan!
你很清楚他有多重要, 谁在这样的情况下做决定.
You know very well, how important he is, who makes the decisions in cases like this.
- 你对此什么意思? - 我的意思是......我的意思.
- What do you mean with that? - I mean... I mean.
来吧,费斯汀.赶紧的. 全体教师正在等你.
Come on, Festim. Hurry. The whole faculty is waiting for you.
费斯汀,过来.
Festim, come here.
这真荒谬.
This is absurd.
你能告诉萨巴夫老师和我们 -
Could you tell teacher Sabaf and us -
- 谁在家里告诉你的 中国是一个修正主义国家?
- who told you at home that China is a revisionistic country?
无论是在家还是其他地方 都没人告诉我.
Nobody told me, neither at home nor in other places.
费斯汀...
Festim...
在这里没人要伤害你. 只要看看我有多好我现在.
Nobody here means to hurt you. Just look at how nice I am right now.
你父亲和你什么事都没有. 只要告诉我们谁告诉你的.
Nothing will happen to your father or you. Just tell us who told you it.
我只是说,哪本书写着, 中国是个社会主义国家.
I just said what the book said, that China is a socialistic country.
我们不要求你背书.
We did not ask you to recite the book.
你必须告诉我们谁 让你在课上说的.
You must tell us who made you say that in the lesson.
为什么德因老师 说你纠正自己?
Why does teacher Djin say that you corrected yourself?
我没有说! 我没说......
I didn't say it! I didn't say...
我没说......
I didn't say...
现在,你最好表现出一定的合作意愿!
Now you better show some will to cooperate!
说实话,我并不反对 你或你的父亲.
To be honest I have nothing against you or your father.
但是,谁教的你父亲 -
But who teached your father that -
- 苏联是 社会主义......呃......资本主义?
- the soviet union is socialistic... uh... capitalistic?
- 修正主义,萨巴夫同志. - 当然.
- Revisionistic, comrade Sabaf. - Of course.
你说什么?现在告诉我们.
What do you say? Tell us now.
你没有赢得什么,萨巴夫同志.
You've got nothing to win by forcing it out, comrade Sabaf.
他什么也没承认, 而我们正在浪费时间.
He's got nothing to confess, and we're wasting our time.
冷静,冷静...
Easy, easy...
我可以用其他方法!
I could use other methods!
费斯汀·托斯库.小心.
Festim Tosku. Be careful.
你和你父亲非常清楚 萨巴夫同志是谁.
You and your father know very well who comrade Sabaf is.
我知道你的家人知道 巡逻车到这里来.
I know your family knows the patrol car that comes here.
叫你父亲明天和我在 办公室明天见面.现在离开这里!
Ask your father to meet me in my office tomorrow. Now get out of here!
这是我的错,萨巴夫同志.
It's my fault, comerade Sabaf.
我没说清楚 政治方面在事件发生的时间.
I was not clear over the political aspects at the time of the event.
哦,我很清楚当这些 修正主义份子藏在哪.
Oh, I know very well where these revisionistic hares hide.
坐下.
Sit down.
费斯汀?
Festim?
- 我告诉你什么? - 没什么.
- What did I tell you? - Nothing.
- 没什么重要的事. - 那你为什么哭?
- Nothing important. - Then why are you crying?
各位同事,萨巴夫同志 是从党委回来, -
Colleagues, comrade Sabaf is back from the party comittee, -
- 谁给了新口号.
- who's given new slogans.
亲爱的同志们,亲爱的同事们：
Dear comrades, dear colleagues:
在一个半月后. 党中央政治局一位委员 -
In one and a half months. a member of the party -
- 将乘车在高速公路上 沿着我们村子驶过.
- will drive by on the highway that runs along our village.
我目前无法告诉你们是谁.
I cannot currently tell you who it is.
出于安全原因.
Security reasons.
也许他会在我们村停下.
Maybe he'll stop by in our village.
因此,我们将搞一个 口号的活动.
Therefore we will start a campaign to renew the slogans.
让我们开始. 德因,这次我们给大家：
Let's begin. Djin, this time we give you:
“中国阿尔巴尼亚友谊万岁.”
"Long Live the Chinese-Albanian friendship."
谢谢你,校长.
Thank you, headmaster.
德因,-
Djin, -
- 你也要负责 公路沿线的口号.
- you'll also be in charge for the work with the slogans along the highway.
在那显示出“恩维尔·霍查”（总书记） 字母要越大越好.
There it will read "Enver Hoxha", with as large letters as possible.
军队会帮助你.
The army will help you.
帕什克,你负责口号： “工人阶级的党万岁.”
Pashk, you got: "Long Live the Worker's Party."
我感谢党.
I thank the party.
安德烈 -
Andr? -
- 你的新口号是：
- your new slogan is:
要让工作,思想和生活 充满革命的意识.
Work, think and live like a revolutionary.
谢谢.
Thank you.
现在轮到你,黛安娜.
And now it's your turn, Diana.
为表扬你承担义务, 我们给你口号：
Because we praise your commitment, we give you:
“加强无产阶级专政, 加强社会民主主义.”
"The Stronger the Dictature of the Proletariate, the Stronger the Social Democracy.
我就知道.
I knew it.
对不起,你是怎么知道的?
Excuse me, what did you know?
你喜欢给 我很长的口号.
That you enjoy to give me mile long slogans.
告诉我,同志,你这 公报私仇要持续多久?
Tell me, comrade, how long will you carry on this personal revenge of yours?
以个人目的使用口号是耻辱.
It's a shame using slogans as personal objects.
戴安娜,这是党委的 决定,不是我.
Diana, it's the party comittee that decides, not me.
而且为什么我会想要报复你? 你有料反对口号?
And why would I want to take any revenge on you? Have you got anything against slogans?
我向大家强调 这个口号 -
I emphasize for everyone that this slogan -
- 是第七届党代会定的.
- was made on the 7th Party Congress.
- 同志,我有个建议. - 什么?
- Comrade, I have a suggestion. - What?
我会用我的“中国 - 阿尔巴尼亚” 口号与戴安娜的交换.
I'll exchange my "Chinese-Albanian" slogan with Diana's.
别问了!
That's out of question!
我们不会坐在这为口号讨价还价 只因有人突发奇想!
We will not sit here and bargain with slogans just because someone has a whim!
- 但是... - 没有但是!
- But... - No buts!
- 只是个建议. - 没有建议或抗议!
- It was just a suggestion. - No suggestions or protests!
这些口号是我们的政治任务.
The slogans are our political tasks.
但是如果有人反对口号, 事情的性质就变了!
But if someone is against slogans, thing's will change!
米拉,因为你的口号依然 很有创意,我们不会改变它：
M'ira, since your slogan still is of current interest, we won't change it:
“忘记的敌人最危险.”
"The Most Dangerous Enemy is the One That Is Forgotten."
非常感谢,同志.
Thanks a lot, comrade.
扎娜.
Zana.
“人民崛起,党在前进.”
"The People Rise, the Party Forward."
谢谢,同志.
Thanks, comrade.
就这样.谢谢.
That's all. Thanks.
别想啦.
Don't think about it.
我会帮你.
I'll help you.
我们可以一起做. 或者我自己来.
We could do it together. Or I could do it on my own.
只会花我两个星期天.
It will only take me two Sundays.
多谢.
Thanks a lot.
- 晚安,安德烈. - 晚安.
- God night, Andr? - God night.
赶快!
Come on!
赶快!抓紧!
Come on! Hurry!
- 你有一张图片? - 把它向左一点.
- Have you got a picture? - Turn it a little to the left.
欢迎.
Welcome.
- 祝贺这新电视. - 谢谢.
- Congratulations to the new TV. - Thanks.
祝贺.
Congratulations.
是我,安德烈.
It's just me, Andr?
放羊的塞尔曼·托斯库, 从雨中来.
Goat farmer Selman Tosku, comes out of the rain.
你来这里不是为说这个?
You're not coming here just to say that?
我来请你为我 给政府写信.
I come to ask you to write a letter to the government for me.
我不会读也不会写.
I can't read nor write.
我活得很可怜.
I live very poor.
我住的小屋随时都会倒塌 砸在我头上.
The cabin I'm living in is threatening to fall apart over my head.
冬天,我的儿子费斯汀 去朋友那里一起住.
In the winter, my son Festim, sleeps at friends of his.
你知道?
And you know what?
在雨天我只要躺下睡觉, 雨水就掉在我鼻子上.
One rainy day when I lay sleeping, it began to drop on my nose.
我总以为有人在舔我, 或者冲着我撒尿.
I thought that someone was licking me, or maybe pissing on me.
去和村委会谈谈.
Talk to the village council about it.
你认为谁会听我的?
Who do you think will listen to me?
我会很喜欢住在 合住的房子里.
I would really like to live in one of the cooperative houses.
还有别人,邻居,儿童...
There's people, neighbors, children...
有一个地方,我可以说.
A place where I can talk.
进来,学校的门是放着的.
Come in. The door to the school is open.
坐到火炉.
Sit down at the stove.
对不起...
I'm sorry...
你可以写.
You can write.
不要忘记告诉 他们漏雨的情况.
Don't forget to tell them about the leakage.
当然.但现在让我写.
Of course not. But let me write now.
请你让我写?相信我. 我不会忘记漏雨的事.
Will you please let me write? Trust me. I won't forget about the leakage.
我相信你.
I trust you.
等等.
Wait.
也许你最好别提漏雨.
Maybe you'd better not mention the leakage.
看上去微不足道.
It could seem petty.
擦掉漏雨的内容.
Wipe that about the leakage.
我不写漏雨,好吧?
I won't write about the leakage, okay?
塞尔曼,我写完了.
Selman, I'm finished.
在你把它放进信封前, 能读给我听?
Before you put it in the envelope, could you read it to me?
“申请.”
"Application."
“我出生在这个村庄 一直住在一个小屋里.”
"I'm born in this village and have always lived in the same cabin."
“我的生活没什么可说的,-”
"As there isn't much to say about my life, -"
“- 我直入主题.”
"- I will go straight to the main cause."
“我一直诚实地工作.”
"I've always worked honestly."
“还是修不起我快塌了的小屋 -”
"Still I cannot afford to repair my cabin, which could fall apart -"
“- 直到现在.”
"- any time now."
怎么了?
What is it?
不,没什么.心难受. -
No, nothing. It hurts. -
- 继续,都读了. - 但是你怎么了?
- Continue, read it all. - But what is it?
心难受 -
It hurts -
- 听别人谈论我的生活.
- hearing others talk about my life.
- 伤害了谁? - 我自己!
- Hurts who? - Myself!
把你的信明天发到村里.
Take your letter and send it to the village tomorrow.
不,读到底.我会的.
No, read the end. I'll do.
“充满希望...”
"Hopeful..."
怎么了,塞尔曼?
What is it, Selman?
要表现得像个大人!
Behave like a grownup man!
这信送到后,你认为他们会给 我一个新房子吗?
Do you think they'll give me a new house after this letter?
有可能.
Maybe.
安德烈,请.
Andr? please.
再读一遍. 我想听听你写了什么.
Read it one more time. I want to hear what you've written.
- 当然,别再流眼泪了! - 我只是想再听一次.
- Sure, but no more tears! - I just want to hear it one more time.
“我出生在这个村庄 一直住在一个小屋里.”
"I'm born in this village and have always lived in the same cabin."
“我的生活没什么可说的,我直入主题.”
"As there isn't much to say about my life, I will go straight to the main cause.
“我一直诚实地工作.”
"I've always worked honestly."
“还是修不起我快塌了的小屋 -”
"Still I cannot afford to repair my cabin, which could fall apart -"
“- 直到现在.”
"- any time now."
“充满希望并相信党,-”
"Hopeful and with trust to the party, -"
“- 我希望可以解决 我的问题.”
"- I hope my problem can be solved."
晚安.
Good night.
别问我了. 我不会再读这封信了.
Don't ask me about it. I won't read the letter one more time.
已经很晚了. 回家睡觉去.
It's late. Go home and go to bed.
这不是我来这里的原因.
That's not the reason why I'm here.
你知道我为什么回来?
Do you know why I came back?
我只是想,怎么能 没感谢你就离开?
I just thought, how could I leave without thanking you?
你为我做了这么多.
You've done so much for me.
我可以回报你什么?
What can I give you in return?
西红柿?板栗?大蒜?
Tomatoes Chestnut? Garlic?
我这么做不是为西红柿.
I didn't do it for tomatoes.
这没什么. 我只是写下你告诉我的.
It was nothing. I just wrote down what you told me.
但我想给你些东西.
But I want to give you something for it.
- 好,给我些大蒜吧. - 我自己去拿.
- OK, then give me some garlic. - I'll bring it myself.
我很抱歉我的行为.
And I'm sorry for my behaviour.
晚安.
Good night.
- 是谁呀? - 开门,是我!
- Who is it? - Unlock, it's me!
- 又是你!这次又是什么? - 我带来了大蒜.
- You again! What is it now? - I come with garlic.
在这个时候!
In this hour!
- 也许一直等到明天. - 你猜我还有什么.
- Maybe it could have waited until tomorrow. - Guess what more I have with me.
- 梅酒,也许? - 正确.
- Raki, maybe? - Correct.
谢谢,我真的很需要.
Thanks, I really needed that.
尝一下!
Taste it!
很好.
Very good.
不,不...
No, no...
我不会再读了这封信.
I won't read the letter again.
嗯,我想我不该强迫你.
Well, I guess I shouldn't force you.
但是,我们别争了.
But let's not argue.
- 我只是来给你梅酒. - 我明白.
- I just came to give you the raki. - I understand.
晚安.
Good night.
一起团结工作 加强同志友爱.
Working together strengthens the camaraderie.
亲爱的同学们.
Dear students.
亲爱的老师们.
Dear teachers.
我代表党 -
On account of the Party -
- 由衷地感谢你们完成这些口号.
- I would like to thank you for the work you've done with the slogans.
这一圈就这么多.
That's all in this round.
昨天我发现有些石头失踪.
Yesterday I saw that the e's were missing. Some stones are missing.
- 那些石头自己移动. - 我很生气!
- Stones moving themselves. - I get mad!
- 医生们称之为压力. - 我已经为口号工作了17年!
- The doctors call it stress. - I've worked with slogans for 17 years!
- 有没有消息? - 没什么.
- Any news? - Not much.
天气真好.
The weather's nice.
- 你今天下午有课吗? - 没有.
- Are you teaching this afternoon? - No.
- 我们应该走到口号那儿? - 我三天前在那里.
- Should we walk over to the slogans? - I was there three days ago.
当然,如果你这么说.
Sure, if you say so.
OK.
你抽烟吗?
Do you smoke?
偶尔.
Now and then.
我喜欢因为它 让我头晕目眩.
I like it because it makes me dizzy.
政治局的委员 将到这停下, -
The members of the politburo will stop by here, -
- 还有这里, -
- and here, -
- 前方口号： “党是幸福之父.”
- in front of the slogan: "The Party is the Father of Happiness."
进来.
Come in.
- 你身后没关门? - 这不是我来这的原因.
- Don't you close your door after you? - That's not the reason why I'm here.
- 我的口号被毁了. - 先关上门.
- It's the destroyed slogan of mine. - Close the door anyway.
- 是不是有人看到? - 没有.
- Did someone see you? - No.
扎碧特,-
Zabit, -
- 农业合作社今年产量如何?
- how was the output of the cooperative this year?
真糟!每公顷两吨.
Terrible! Two tons per hectare.
这并不可怕. 就像各地一样.
That's not terrible. It was like that everywhere.
每公顷2.2吨.
2,2 tons per hectare.
你能对一个只想着女人的
What could you expect with a cooperative leader -
- 农业合作社领导指望什么?
- who only thinks about ladies?
你见过扎娜的儿子吗?
Have you seen Zana's son?
他喜欢吹领导的鼻子!
He's like blown out of the nose of the leader!
这是怎么回事?
What's going on?
塞尔曼·托斯库!
Selman Tosku!
我以人民的名义逮捕你.
I arrest you in the name of the people.
同志们.
Comrades.
今天我们聚集在这里揭露 人民公敌：塞尔曼·托斯库.
We have gathered here today to reveal an enemy of the people: Selman Tosku.
他来自本地区一个最反动的家庭.
He comes from one of the most reactionary families in the district.
你们了解他.
You know him well.
就是他,塞尔曼 -
It's he, Selman, -
- 他机关算尽反对我们.
- who's thought out an advanced way to fight us.
他破坏了我们的口号 -
He destroys our slogans, -
- 孩子们热情辛苦工作的成果.
- the ones that the children have laid down with hard work and love.
这些口号蒙蔽塞尔曼.
These slogans have blinded Selman.
认真听好,塞尔曼·托斯库.
Listen real good, Selman Tosku.
即使在毒蛇的嘴里 -
Even in the mouth of a serpent -
- 我们也会找到你!
- we would have found you!
尊敬的首长,-
Your honour, -
- 你没有证据审判我.
- you judge me without reason.
我是无辜的.
I'm innocent.
我没有做任何事.
I haven't done anything.
我从来没有碰过那些口号.
I never touched the slogans.
尊敬的首长,我能说些什么吗?
Your honour, may I say something?
好.
Yes.
我了解塞尔曼.
I know Selman well.
他可能是个贫穷的牧羊人, 但他是个好人.
He may be a poor goat farmer, but he's a good man.
他不能读写 他不能数他的山羊.
He can't read or write and he can not count his goats.
他甚至不知道 口号什么意思.
He doesn't even know what the slogans mean.
他们缺少他的动机.
They lack meaning to him.
你怎么能判决 一个文盲 -
How can you judge an analphabet -
- 仅为了一些和他无关的事?
- for an act that doesn't mean anything to him?
塞尔曼·托斯库 -
Selman Tosku -
- 一个文盲 -
- is so much an analphabet -
- 他破坏了 米拉的口号：
- that he sabotaged the slogan of M'ira's:
“忘记的敌人最危险.”
"The Most Dangerous Enemy Is the One That Is Forgotten."
塞尔曼·托斯库,谢谢你 教我们的.你说得太对了.
Selman Tosku, thank you for what you've teached us. You're so right.
我们永远不会忘记你!
We will never forget you!
至于你,安德烈 -
As for you, Andr? -
- 我能说的是, 你还很年轻.
- all I can say is that you're still very young.
有一些事情你不明白.
There are some things you don't not understand.
但是,你将会学到 别介入别人的工作!
But you will learn eventually to not mind others businesses!
把他带走.
Take him away.
那里.
There.
那里将有一个海报： “阿尔巴尼亚 - 坚如磐石”.
There will be a poster reading: "Albania - The Granite Rock".
在那边,在河边： “恩维尔的党”.
And over there, at the riverside: "Enver Party".
把那该死的发动机关掉!
Stop that goddamned motor!
如果我关掉它,它不会再次启动.
If I stop it, it won't start again.
这是个完美的地方 -
It's a perfect place -
- 对停车来说.
- for the car to stop.
不要忘记,人们应该 站在道路两侧.
Don't forget that people should stand at both sides of the road.
我希望他们会开车进村! 我们必须为任何事情做好准备.
I hope they'll drive into the village! We must be prepared for anything.
让我们总结一下.
Let's summarize.
“阿尔巴尼亚人民万岁.”
"Long Live the Albanian People."
“无产阶级专政万岁, 团结稳定坚如磐石.”
"Long Live the Dictature of the Proletariat, Steady as the Primary Rock."
他当然会握住我的手 -
And he will of course shake my hand -
- 并用他的胳膊搂住我. 他还会做什么!
- and put his arm around me. What else could he do!
我们去小学,去我们这一区 的边界找莱什.
Let's got o the small school, to Lesh in the outskirts of our district.
在世界尽头!
At the end of the world!
“越南将会获胜”
"VIETNAM WILL WIN"
我没想到在这里见到你,萨巴夫同志.
I wasn't expecting to see you here, comrade Sabaf.
同志,这是我的荣幸.
Comrade, the pleasure is all mine.
你好.
Greetings.
- 进来. - 我们进来工作的相关业务,莱什.
- Come in. - We come in work related business, Lesh.
对不起, 但今天的教育结束了.
I'm sorry, but the education is over for today.
有什么不对的?
Is something wrong?
是的,莱什.你的口号.
Yes, Lesh. Your slogan.
- 什么?“越南将会获胜”? - 是的,莱什.
- What? "Vietnam Will Win"? - Yes, Lesh.
越南战争已经结束10年了.
The Vietnam war ended 10 years ago.
我简直不敢相信!
I can't believe it!
谁赢了?
Who won?
问题是,你的 口号已经过时了.
The problem is that your slogan is obsolete.
怎么了,莱什?
Has something happened, Lesh?
越南.是北越赢了.
Vietnam. It was The North Vietnam who won.
越南已经胜利了!
Vietnam has won!
仁慈的祝福,越南赢了!
Goodness gracious, Vietnam won!
他们赢了!感谢上帝.
They won! Thank God.
我每晚都祈祷越南会取胜. 他们真是些狡猾的小家伙.
I prayed every night that the Vietnamese would win. They're dodgy little fellows.
你的口号必须被马上毁掉.
Your slogan must be destroyed immidiately.
莱什,我们是老朋友了,对吧?
Lesh, we're old friends, aren't we?
我们一起在村里下棋.
We've played chess together in the village.
我从没想过我会走这么远.
I never thought I would have to go to these lenghts.
我必须报告给全体教师 这是一种意识形态的问题.
I'll have to report it to the faculty as an ideological matter.
这真是不可原谅,莱什, 我甚至可以认真地说!
It's really unforgivable, Lesh, I would even say serious!
但我花了很久才弄好口号.
But I got it a long time ago.
在你来到这里之前,同志!
Long before you came here, comrade!
试着去理解!你跟不上时代了.
Try to understand! You're not following the news of the world.
我们可以留住它作为 历史的记忆.
We could keep it like a historical memory.
对,就是这样!
Yes, exactly!
已经够了! 马上拆除这个口号!
Enough already! Remove this slogan immidiately!
莱什,听着.
Lesh, listen.
我不得不在教师会议 上提及此事.
I'll have to bring this up on the faculty meeting.
- 你不会生我的气吧? - 不,没关系这是很好的.
- You won't be mad at me? - No. It's good.
你好.
Good day.
那么,莱什. 告诉我们发生了什么事.
Well, Lesh. Tell us what happened.
我很抱歉,但你是什么意思?
I'm sorry, but what do you mean?
什么?告诉我们为什么你 的口号还在.
What? Tell us why your slogan is still there.
让我们来完成这件事.
Let's finish this matter.
你把纸条拿反了.
You're holding the paper upside down.
谢谢.
Thanks.
同志们
Comrades.
党和
The Party.
人民
The People.
我只服从党的指示.
I only followed the orders from the Party.
在那之后,没有人告诉 我要改变口号.
And after that no one has asked me to change slogan.
我和我的学生们已尽可能 让口号保持良好的状态.
I and my students have done our best to keep it in good shape.
好.
Good.
我们唯一可以责怪莱什的, -
The only thing we can blame Lesh for, -
- 是他对世界各地的 革命胜利缺乏兴趣.
- is his deficient interest for the success of the revolution around the world.
如果中央政治局的委员 看到这口号会怎么想?
What would the member of the politburo have thinked if he saw the slogan?
我同意.
I agree.
但现在我的意思是 莱什需要一个新口号.
But now I mean that Lesh needs a new slogan.
唯一的问题是我们不能 向党中央求教.
The only problem is we can't ask for advice from the Party.
萨巴夫同志,我建议 给他一个简短的口号.
Comrade Sabaf, I suggest we give him a short slogan.
他住的偏远口号不强制.
Besides he lives so far away that a slogan is not compulsory.
你是什么意思,帕什克?
What do you mean, Pashk?
你我都知道 -
You know as much as I do -
- 那些资本主义国家总是嘲弄越南.
- that the capitalistic countries always have played with Vietnam.
莱什,毁掉那口号! 让我们完成这件事!
Lesh, destroy the slogan! Let's finish this matter!
同志们,我毕生忠实地为这口号工作.
Comrades, I've worked faithfully all my life with that slogan.
没有人会怀疑你的忠实.
No one doubts that you've handled in good faith.
但这个口号已经 10年了,太旧了!
But the slogan is 10 years too old!
- 那就给我一个现代的! - 你在世界尽头,我们给你什么呢?
- So just give me a more modern one! - What could we give you on the end of the world?
无论你想要什么,只要 包括越南这个词.
Whatever you want, as long as the word Vietnam is included
我们有孩子们在等待. 我们不能在这呆一夜.
We've got children waiting. We can't stay here all night.
如果莱什想要一个口号 包括单词越南, -
If Lesh want's a slogan with Vietnam in it, -
“射击,越南,射击,指挥你的炮塔 向着所有的和平谈判.“
"Shoot, Vietnam, Shoot. Direct Your Cannons Towars All Peace Negotiations."
你的口号会是什么?
What will your slogan be?
我不知道.
I don't know.
还没决定.
It's not decided yet.
结尾升调吗, -
High heels or not, -
- 在这被遗忘的村里 没人注意到我.
- no one notices me in this forgotten village anyway.
你,那的!
You there!
老师没告诉你 穿上最好的衣服吗?
Didn't the teacher ask you to take your best clothes on?
这是什么洞? 你的脚趾都露出来了!
What's this hole? Your toes are sticking out!
我就这一双鞋.
I don't have any other.
你,那的!不要只是坐在那里. 到路上来.
You there! Don't just sit there. Come over to the road.
你也是. 每个人都上马路.
You too. Everyone over to the road.
同志,把所有人 转移到另一侧.
Comrade, move someone over to the other side.
赶快! 看上去多几分热情.
Come on! Look a little more enthusiastic.
恩维尔的党!恩维尔的党!
Enver Party! Enver Party!
阿尔巴尼亚 坚如磐石
ALBANIA THE GRANITE ROCK
他来了!
He's coming!
恩维尔的党!恩维尔的党!
Enver Party! Enver Party!
持续抵抗,越南
HOLD STAND, VIETNAM
安德烈 -
Andr? -
- 萨巴夫同志和我想到了 画在墙上的口号.
- comrade Sabaf and I thought about painting a slogan on the wall.
你被赋予画它的荣誉.
You've been given the honour of painting it.
这口号是： “无产阶级专政万岁.”
The slogan is as follows: "Long Live the Dictature of the Proletariat."
还有一件事,安德烈.
And another thing, Andr?
校长和我 都非常关注.
The headmaster and I are very concerned.
最近你和戴安娜的行为 -
Recently your and Diana's behaviour has -
- 令人关注.
- awoken concern.
你在村民们眼中不是个好模范.
You've not been a good role model in the eyes of the village.
你很清楚,党 -
You know very well that the Party -
- 考虑到教师的道德是圣洁的.
- considers a teachers moral to be holy.
因此,我们建议区教委 -
Therefore we have suggested to the districts education comittee -
- 将戴安娜会被调到 另一个村子.
- that Diana's transfered to another village.
当然很远.
Far away, of course.
这样一来,你会更在乎 你在学校的事业.
That way, you will care more about your school undertakings.
特别是口号的工作.同意?
Especially in the work with the slogans. Agreed?
是.
Yes.
阳台上的孩子
A child on a balcony
把花扔向头盔
is throwing flowers down on the helmets
齐步行军前进
forward march
刺刀都在闪耀.
the bayonets are shining.
坚持,老师!
Hang on, teacher!
赶快!
Hurry!
从那下来!
Get down from there!
安德烈
Andr?
党和人民是因为你 才开这次会的.
The party and the people are having this meeting only because of you.
你绘制口号是用手还是用脚?
Did you paint the slogan with your hands or with your feet?
很有趣.
Very fun.
党和人民 很想知道 -
The party and the people would very much want to know -
- 谁让你那样画口号的?
- who asked you to paint the slogan that way?
同志们,我很抱歉那个错误.
I'm sorry about the faults, comrades.
我没从任何人得到指示, 萨巴夫同志.
I haven't got orders from anyone, comrade Sabaf.
我尽可能让口号好看.
I did my best to make the slogan look good.
但它并没有变得好看 -
But it was didn't turn out very well -
- 因为墙是扭曲的.
- because the wall was warped.
拜托!
Please!
如果你只谈墙 和路径,我们永远都没完!
If you only talk about walls and paths, we'll never finish!
那你的意思是什么原因?
So what do you mean is the reason?
我可以告诉你们.同志们.
I can tell you that. Comrades.
这不仅仅是 -
This isn't just about -
- 安德烈画口号 没有必要的激情.
- Andr?painting the slogan without the necessary passion.
问题比这更严重.安德烈.
The problem runs deeper than that. Andr?
他刚来时,就给塞尔曼·托斯库烟.
From the moment he arrived, he gave cigarettes to Selman Tosku.
他成为了他的朋友, 在法庭上捍卫他.
He became his friend and defended him in the court.
而这还不是全部!
And that's not all!
党中央政治局委员驶过时, 他没有拍手鼓掌!
When the member of the politburo drove by, he didn't clap his hands!
是的,萨巴夫同志. 你误导.
Yes, comrade Sabaf. You're misinformed.
嗯,是的,你鼓掌了. 但还是不够的热情!
Well yes, you applaused. But it wasn't enthusiastic enough!
但最糟糕的事是偷着和法语老师调情.
But the worst thing is the secret flirting with the french teacher.
就是他!
It's him!
他!
Him!
同志们, -
Comrades, -
- 这正是人民公敌的行为!
- that's exactly how an enemy of the people behaves!
是的,一个人民的敌人!
Yes, an enemy of the people!
冷静,萨巴夫同志.
Take it easy, comrade Sabaf.
我不是说要减轻他的责任, -
I do not mean to lessen his slip-ups, -
- 但让我们和平安静地看问题.
- but let us look at the problem in peace and quiet.
安德烈.你可以离开我们,直到 党在这个问题上做出决定.
Andr? you may leave us until the Party has decided in the matter.
我很担心你.
I was worried for you.
我已经等很久了.
I've been waiting long.
这一次党选择宽容.
This time the Party chose to be indulgent.
你下放到农业合作社 去劳动6个月 -
You escape with six months of hard labour -
- 隆姆同志在那是领导.
- in the cooperative where comrade Lume is the leader.
- 萝拉. - 老师!
- Lola. - Teacher!
你累吗?
Are you tired?
现在,我们用砖块写口号. 这很容易!
Now we write all the slogans with bricks. It's much easier!
但还是要一砖一砖地摆.
But it's still brick after brick.
现在走吧.
Let's go now.
贝斯姆和艾斯特勒夫, 你俩装载拖拉机.
Besim and Estref, you load the tractor.
你们开始收庄稼. 安德烈.你跟着别人做.
You begin to reap. Andr? you follow the others.
看你的这双手不是劳作用的, 而是为享受用的.
These hands of yours are not made for work, but for pleasure.
他完成了所有的工作, 他做工非常勤奋.
He's done all the tasks he was asked to do with great diligence.
他帮助了我们读懂党的颂歌.
He helped us to read the Party Song.
我还能说什么?帮帮我, 同志们.我说得对吧?
What more can I say? Help me, comrades. Am I right, or?
是,你是对的. 他勤奋工作.
Yes, you're right. He's worked diligently.
而且他没有往后站.
And he didn't stand back physically.
同志们.
Comrades.
我诚心诚意感谢你们.
I thank you of all my heart.
我给你们的口号是：
The slogan I give you is:
“稻堆堆得圆又圆,社员堆稻上了天. 撕片白云擦擦汗,凑上太阳抽根烟.”
"May the Campaign of Sowing and Harvesting be Crowned with Luck."
很适合在合作社的工作.
It fits the work you did in the cooperative.
还有一件事,安德烈.
One more thing, Andr?
最近 -
Recently -
- 我们一直在用砖头 而不是石头.
- we've been using bricks instead of rocks.
这样更有利于实用和美观.
It gives many practical and aesthetic benefits.
不再需要把岩石刷白,-
It's no longer necessary to bleach the rocks, -
- 下雨和动物们 再也不能破坏口号.
- and rain and domestic animals can no longer destroy the slogans.
但又发生了新问题. 学生们能把砖偷走.
But a new problem has arised. The students can steal the bricks.
党委已对此表示严正关切. 当然,他们是对的.
The Party comittee has expressed concerns over this. And of course they're right.
人们必须能够 表达自己的感受, -
The people must be able to express their feelings, -
- 那是当然的.
- spontaneously.
自然自己动手.
Naturally and with their own hands.
- 你明白吗? - 是.谢谢.
- Do you understand? - Yes. Thanks.
现在去吧.你全班都在校园等你.
Go now. Your class is waiting for you at the school yard.
“稻堆堆得圆又圆,社员堆稻上了天. 撕片白云擦擦汗,凑上太阳抽根烟.”
"May the Campaign of Sowing and Harvesting be Crowned with Luck."
但是老师,那有42个字母.
But teacher, that's 42 letters.
用砖头还是石头,老师?
In brick or rocks, teacher?
用石头.
In rock.
就像以前一样.
Just like before.
爱德华译制
English translation: x264